[SPEAKER_00]: Why is first jhāna wholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is jhāna wholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's looted from sensuality and unwholesome things.
[SPEAKER_01]: How?
[SPEAKER_01]: By
[SPEAKER_01]: Establishing the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is how I understand it anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: Establishing the mind to the extent where you sort of... beyond those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Theoretically, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is then?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the principle of sanctuality?
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to say, seeing the seeing the seeing the pain is pleasurable?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how is that possible?
[SPEAKER_00]: What assumption is required for you to keep seeing pain as
[SPEAKER_00]: Enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Get back.
[SPEAKER_01]: Something to do with...
Assumption.
What's the principle of assumption, of upādāna?
[SPEAKER_01]: Assuming sort of something outside of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as we said before, you assume that the pleasure is outside of your desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, in the things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: In whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you don't specify where it is, you assume it's outside of this presently enduring unpleasant desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it starts to... Well, that's why you induce a separate identity to that desire, desire... the identity of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence the assumption of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were to see that it doesn't matter the extent of your pleasure, it's within the painful desire, thus it's unpleasant, you will stop regarding it as separately pleasurable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can only see it as pleasant, see this pleasure, by seeing it separate from the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Outside of the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's fully enclosed within the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were to see that, you wouldn't see it as pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that is the principle of upādāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the principle of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is the principle that you abandon in the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why, theoretically, it is still possible
[SPEAKER_00]: to maintain some ignorance, despite developing the mind in the first jhāna, but it's highly unlikely.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why jhānas in themselves are very wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's unlikely you would be abandoning the wrong assumptions and principles without a degree of understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what's called right contemplation, basically, right mind establishment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's temporary liberation, or... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's a liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's completely undoing the assumptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, obviously, it's the fundamental wisdom in regard to the nature of the assumptions that will then keep you perpetually free from those.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you haven't developed that wisdom, then if you're not establishing the jhāna, then there's certain assumptions might take place again.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even... even so, you could see how... how much less instruction a person who has developed mind to the extent of the first jhāna, how much less instruction that person would need, in order to then fully understand the nature of upādāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what do you think?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: There is not necessarily unwholesome,
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's on the level of assuming it outside, that gets abandoned, and thus establish the first jhāna by abandoning it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, you're withdrawn from centrality, but more specifically...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, not just that...
[SPEAKER_00]: The initial, the initial establishment of mind, the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was thinking it was about...
[SPEAKER_01]: Putting yourself beyond sensuality, if you're saying something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's all a result of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, on a most practical level, well, what did the Buddha say?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the thing that ceases in the first jhāna?
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what is the necessary basis for speech?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: According to first jhāna, Tiruvannāmalai is correct.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, Pitaka Vichara.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thinking and exploring, thinking and pondering is a necessary basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is a necessary basis for engagement with external central objects?
[SPEAKER_01]: For the sake of chasing pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is a necessary basis for that?
[SPEAKER_00]: What does it need to be there enduring in order for you to be making effort and performing actions towards physical sense objects?
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in between?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can have thoughts without needing to seek sensual... What is specifically tied to sensual gratification?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is a necessary phenomenon that needs to be present?
[SPEAKER_00]: To be there for you to chase after.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's absolutely... And that's the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if things you're about to do are not necessarily immoral or wrong, if you're doing them out of the desire, they are sensual.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're not engaging them with desire, there's no desire, they're not sensual.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the desire that determines the context, whether it's the assumption of sensuality or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why... And that's why certain things you cannot do
[SPEAKER_00]: Without desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's that's why I, you know, I like to translate karma as sense desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it comes from the word desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is more accurate.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, back on the principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: What parallels can you draw then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Desire is a necessary basis for sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They are assumed to be pleasant separately.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Outside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Outside of this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, outside of the desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Separate to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: After this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you think that relates then with the thinking and pondering?
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is, you know, can be quite neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a routine desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the corresponding engagement of speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Breaking into speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having thought and pondered, one breaks into speech, as the Buddha translated it, as the Buddha said it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that doesn't quite make sense to me right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that would imply...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm thinking that that would imply that speech is rooted in desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: That can't be right.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, like, listen.
[SPEAKER_00]: I said...
[SPEAKER_00]: I said it from the start.
[SPEAKER_00]: Desire is the necessary basis for sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's one thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't mix it now with thinking and pondering and speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thinking and pondering is a necessary basis for speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: The principle of desire in sensuality, as in the principle of assumption,
[SPEAKER_00]: How does that compare to this?
[SPEAKER_00]: But not like, oh, so this is... No, I'm not trying to interject it and sort of permutate the members.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Desire stays there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thinking and pondering free from desire stays there.
[SPEAKER_01]: However, there is a certain principle that's in common to both.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so desire is the necessary basis for engagement, gratification of a sense of desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, incidentally, as you already said it, incidentally, but it was also a right answer as well, just not what I was asking in time,
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you have desire without a thought of desire?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is a desire, unless it's your mental thought, an inclination, a craving, an intention?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Affected with lust, as the Buddha would say, desire is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there can be thinking and pondering with...
[SPEAKER_00]: Without.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as I said, you always have to start...
[SPEAKER_00]: In fact, that would be first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you only have to start in the reverse order.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, thinking and pondering with desire is the starting point for an unenlightened mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, thinking and pondering without desire is what you have to develop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you develop that when you stop engaging with your true, just assumption of separation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something, something separate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something external, something outside of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, to that extent,
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not addressing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: To that extent, it's not on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: To that extent, it's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: To that extent, it's secondary.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's over there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And to that extent, you remain affected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so that... and that... it's... because it's over there, it implies me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It reaffirms this whole thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, desire and sensuality, and thinking and pondering without desire, and speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: What are they common?
[SPEAKER_00]: What nature do they share?
[SPEAKER_01]: That one determines the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: That one is the necessary basis for the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, ignorance, say, ignorance of the necessary basis, what is that result?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, take the practical example.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignorance, the pleasure you project to be in sense objects, is fully within the context of your desire of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot be before, after, not even for a second later.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always within.
[SPEAKER_00]: You not knowing that, what does that lack of knowledge result in?
[SPEAKER_00]: Chasing after sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why would you be chasing after sense objects over there?
[SPEAKER_00]: For the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do you think pleasure is there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do you think pleasure is there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's felt as pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: These things... Well, no, it's felt as pleasant, but why over there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you're clearly feeling the prospect of sense-object-pleasant, before you get to sense-object, yet you're going to sense-object, but you're feeling already pleasant on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why are you going to sense-object, then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you think that's... Because you think it's outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you think, this pleasure I'm feeling, it's over there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: As ridiculous as it sounds, that is in its core of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what's completely gratuitous assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that assumption is the result of you ignoring the fundamental context of necessarily enduring desire for any engagement, even if you are not fully conscious of your desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whenever you're engaging with sense objects, for the sake of pleasure, there needs to be an underlying container of desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: That it's presently enduring unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's... knowing that means the gratuitous separation induced by your assumption won't be there anymore, or certainly won't be fueled.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not knowing that means this separation is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the separation is that... the separation is both that the pleasure is in the thing that I'm chasing after and it's in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: It remains in the domain that's always out there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, ironically, even your assumption of separation is within the context of the present-day duty and desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't truly step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, once you fully understand that, it becomes inconceivable for you to think in those terms anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as you said then, what unites them is a necessary basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is the necessary basis...
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, what is... what would... what would it result to?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the necessary basis of thinking and pondering, necessary basis for speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: What would then ignorance of that context, of that order, of that container, what would that result... result to in regard to speech?
[SPEAKER_01]: The speech is somehow separate from your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: In what manner?
[SPEAKER_00]: Describe the characteristics of separation.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's try this with him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're speaking now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that speech independent of the simultaneously presently enduring thinking and pondering behind it?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that speech before you think and ponder?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that speech after you've been thinking and pondering?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is the nature of that speech... Not even a nanosecond after thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, but is that speech in its own domain?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it has its own domain, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why people then assume separation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not the same as thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's not the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you see it as a result of your thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, you see sensual pursuit as a result of your desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Aiming at the result of your desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what's in common, as I said, when I asked you initially, to that separation?
[SPEAKER_00]: Assuming outside in regard to the inside.
[SPEAKER_00]: Assuming it to be external.
[SPEAKER_01]: Assuming speech to be external to your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: To thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which then makes you ignorant of the domain of thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which then makes you incapable of establishing the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're putting...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might be perfectly restrained in doing the centrality, but you still carry on the same principle of the same assumption in regard to the domain of your speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, rather than seeing thinking and pondering through the speech, because that's the only way
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to see your speech within thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to see the possibility of your speech within thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, you have to see a possibility of your sense desires within the pressure of the desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, when I'm speaking, then when I'm not speaking, yeah, but there's a possibility to break into speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The speech domain is always that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you assume that possibility, at least, to be separate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: From the thinking, from the container, to be outside of the container of thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you fully understand this, you will be establishing the first jhāna and you will be dwelling in it, as the Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you're walking, sitting, lying down, going to the toilet, the mind will be in that establishment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, hang on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's said the speech ceases.
[SPEAKER_00]: Speech in the first jhāna ceases.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because in order for you to speak,
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to maintain neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not an unwholesome assumption like sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a neutral assumption of external domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: To the thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: To the thought that you engage with through speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that assumption is like a functional... You step outside the thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to step outside of thought in order to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, what happens?
[SPEAKER_00]: Inner mind, stepping outside of the thought, carries the assumption of this is outside of the thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you... that's why first jhāna is necessary for final knowledge, for arahantship or for being anāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to at least experience it in a sense of
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can... it's possible to speak without
[SPEAKER_00]: Without assuming.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without assuming the extent, without giving it a separate identity.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's possible to speak without losing the context of the necessary container, necessary basis of thinking and pondering as a domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even then, you have to turn away from thinking and pondering in order to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to break into speech, as the Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the first jhāna,
[SPEAKER_00]: You get to, like, surmount that, so that you understand, or rather it would then result in your understanding, that that does not require an assumption of an external world where the speech occurs.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can you say that... although, right now, you're not speaking, speech is there, the domain of speech is there,
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there's always the possibility for you to break out into speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, but more accurately...
[SPEAKER_00]: That possibility is also there, as a possibility, because the mind hasn't been established on the domain of thinking and pondering properly enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the possibility of speech is not the same thing as thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's within... everything is within thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the certain thoughts and certain ponders.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can break into speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can turn away from its own nature in order to speak, in order to express it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's just the same as saying nothing can be experienced apart from mentally, as a kind of mental phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, nothing can be experienced outside of the container of mental phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are different aspects within that, but there is nothing separate to it, as in external to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, thinking about pure matter presents itself as a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you could say that within this domain of thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, if you develop thinking and pondering rightly, if you develop first jhāna, you are free from conceivings.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you had any understanding of our principle of conceivings and upādāna, there would be more than enough for you to fully understand it and free yourself entirely.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the speech ceases, because you saw it as fully contained.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter how far, how long, how loud you might be speaking, how much you have been speaking, how much you will be speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can never step outside of the domain of thinking and pondering required to be there enduring simultaneously with your speech, but also required for you to not think about it in order to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you break into speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't be...
[SPEAKER_00]: Thinking about what you're speaking and speaking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your speaking becomes your thinking about what you're speaking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why you turn away from thinking about...
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why it's neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no problem with it, but there is a problem for somebody who hasn't been freed from assumptions, from upādāna, because any principle of of putting second as first, then first as second, is the principle that is then maintaining the fundamental ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to learn how to speak without putting the speech first and thought second.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without forgetting.
[SPEAKER_00]: And without refusing to speak ever again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then you're still within the possibility of speaking.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's going to be even harder for you to understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, without kind of losing sight of the necessary basis for that speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, speech ceases when you became
[SPEAKER_00]: When you develop full clarity in regard to the nature of speech being always within the container of thinking and pondering, you dwell on that newly clarified context long enough, at least for that time, as a result of your dwelling on that imperturbable nature, imperturbable order, you become unable to sort of even direct yourself, so to speak, towards possibility of speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, the actual speech has ceased.
[SPEAKER_00]: The actual speech has ceased.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the speech is there when you are within the possibilities of saying something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But whether you are saying something, whether you are abstaining from speaking, whether there are possibilities, all that is within the presently enduring thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because for you now, you might say, okay, my thinking and pondering is limited, but the possibilities of speaking, you still kind of gratuitously assume as belonging to the speech domain, which you gratuitously assume to be external, not as if belonging to the thinking and pondering domain, which is neither external nor internal.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: External... Internal becomes defined when you externalize things with your gratuitous assumptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, in return, they're defined, which is not external.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, that's my internal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Me, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is the principle for all the jhānas.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why... Is there more than this?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the second jhāna, thinking and pondering would cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because thinking and pondering has been assumed external in regard to what's then in the second jhāna, what's the necessary basis for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Joy, pity...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: A certain agreeable... Happiness.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...economity, sort of agreeability of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is not much movement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same principle then goes to the immaterial establishments of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the... so, which... Like, for example, breathing stops.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the four jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because... Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you do assume movement of the breath to be external to the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You... tiny bit, you still assume it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Failing to see that... how can they even... how can any notion of breath even be conceivable?
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's not defined entirely within the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the subtlest of assumptions are the ones like third jhāna, fourth jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as I said, it's assumption in its nature of assuming external while it's actually within it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not assumption necessarily in the nature of containing ignorance and lust and aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as long as...
[SPEAKER_00]: I just want to clarify that so people don't go, ah, assumption, assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, as I said, theoretically, Puthujana can develop jhānas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I see what you mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: And still remain ignorant of the fundamental nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm used to the word assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if he... Like, if Puthujana develops jhāna, you could see how much work he already done.
[SPEAKER_00]: He already done all these structural assumptions he understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: He needs very little instruction then.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by all means, develop the understanding of jhānas.
[SPEAKER_00]: With or without the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's highly unlikely you'll be able to develop it without the right view today.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the only notion of jhānas is through the instruction of the Buddha, which means you will be sufficiently familiar.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the word cease...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, breathing ceases in fourth jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: It literally ceases.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a person's sitting there not breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it isn't just.
[SPEAKER_01]: That they're not breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that they've stopped... Yeah, the reason they're able to not breathe is because they stop assuming life to be external.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Life...
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means it's stopped... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means it stopped requiring external maintenance of breath.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why even the life in itself, it's within the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha called it āya-saṅkhāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: Āya-saṅkhāra, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's another necessary basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: Beyond...
[SPEAKER_00]: But that basis is a bit out of reach... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...for everyone except Samasambuddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: He can... he can direct his intentions toward that basis, as he did.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's time for the target to die.
[SPEAKER_00]: He relinquished the āyusangāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even then he had to wait.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even then he had to eat corrupted meat.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: To get sick and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But... but that's... that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's actually...
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter how subtle you go, how far you go, how far you surmount things.
[SPEAKER_00]: The principle of
[SPEAKER_00]: Contained within.
[SPEAKER_01]: Contained within, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to remain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, so... See, that's why, yeah, you could also see, if on that level, the principle is still maintained, if your body gets killed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You, you know, you haven't gone, you didn't go anywhere, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your body is gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Certain aspect of your form is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the principles that maintain you bound to the form, through these gratuitous assumptions, are still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the core of rebirth.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not rebirthing anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just modifying the environment you're always in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because on that fundamental level, all these assumptions that keep that whole possibilities of these different environments, different lives.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's all within the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all within the principle of assuming external within the internal.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just reapp... not even reappearing again, because it means like you've disappeared.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's actually when you're living, you're dying, you're in between, as the Buddha said, you're reborn, are like yesterday, today, tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no greater mystery to that, than mystery between how was I yesterday, and what am I today, and what will I be tomorrow?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just...
[SPEAKER_00]: Here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Enduring like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Enduring in this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Subjected to change.
[SPEAKER_00]: Subjected to various elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when those elements change sufficiently, next thing you know, or not know, but you are an animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: When those elements change sufficiently, you are a deva.
[SPEAKER_00]: Point of view remains there.
[SPEAKER_00]: The five aggregates remain there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you're ten years older or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or ten years older.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why somebody remembers a previous life, they would have gave the simile.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like somebody who came from one village to the other village to the other village.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then somebody in the last village asked him, where did you come from?
[SPEAKER_00]: And he remembers the village before and village before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were truly traveling through different birds externally, you would have no recollection of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you would be outside to yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That other bird is external to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, cessation of speech, then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Mm-hm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cessation of speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: How would you begin developing it?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, normally... Start, you know, in a broadest manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so, normally... Well, normally... What would be the necessary conditions?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you develop cessation of speech in company?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Go and spend some time on your own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if everybody is perfectly silent, just watching their feet and observing their nostrils.
[SPEAKER_00]: The possibility to talk to them is always there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the domain of speech is always there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you've said, right, I'm not going to speak to anyone.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm really confident.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a matter of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Someone might talk to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a matter of determination.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a matter of still pertaining to that
[SPEAKER_00]: domain that's assumed to be external, and now other people are just reinforcing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you already have four sets of notions about externality of other people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, good luck then fixing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to be physically withdrawn.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, physically withdrawn.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you're not sitting cross-legged, you need to be at least in solitude, where your possibility of being affected by speech...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...is not there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now it's only on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what would you then do, in order to develop for the jhāna?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I guess I acknowledge the possibility of speech as being presence.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does acknowledgement mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: What does that entail?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what do you mean by saying the analogy?
[SPEAKER_01]: What would you like to describe it?
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess, what I want to say, like, so, like, you've got... it's obviously, it's obviously going to be seeing speech as being fully enclosed within thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how to do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: By dwelling on thinking and pondering, I guess.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: How would you dwell on thinking and pondering without implying the possibility of speech?
[SPEAKER_01]: Without simultaneously...
[SPEAKER_01]: So... Ah, so any...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is a possibility of speech?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's a particular type of thought that directs towards breaking the speech away from itself of being a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which you wouldn't be doing if you were on your own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doing what?
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't naturally be breaking out into speech when you're on your own.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, but you would also not be thinking about the possibility of speaking.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'd be lost in your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when you have a voice in your head talking, or a song you can't get rid of, and so on, because you're completely untrained in regards to the domain of the possibility of speech, which is the domain of speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why there is no internal silence, even if...
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, first you have to be silent externally, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: First, you need to practice sensory strength externally, in order to understand the perversion on the inside, and free yourself from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, thinking...
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, the possibility of speech is thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's...
[SPEAKER_00]: Possibility of speech is thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a thought of a particular nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what are the characteristics of that thought?
[SPEAKER_00]: Of the thought?
[SPEAKER_00]: That particular thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is breaking into space.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, go quiet now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And think about possibility to say something.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I want you then to tell me the possibilities of that possibility of saying something.
[SPEAKER_00]: The characteristics of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The characteristics of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Possibility to say something.
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess it's somehow like stepping out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, which one is stepping out?
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so the possibility to speech is about the possibility to step out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, okay, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's like the possibility of going outside of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: You speak because...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you speak because you can.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there's a thing now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's stay on this possibility to step outside.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you know that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like possibility that I will get the pleasure from touching this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I know that while I'm not touching this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That possibility of going out there is here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just that, would you even conceive any notion of out there without this possibility enduring?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, would you be able to conceive the speech and act of speaking externally?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without a possibility to speak, without having thought and pondered with possibility of breaking into speech?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would you be able to speak?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would that constitute speech?
[SPEAKER_00]: Hang on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, hang on.
[SPEAKER_01]: The domain of speech is there, already given.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's the wrong way to go around.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's not go that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, silent, you have possibility to say something.
[SPEAKER_00]: The characteristics of that possibility
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, as you said, that it implies...
[SPEAKER_01]: The possibility to go outside, to... to... to sort of get... step outside of thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... Or this mental domain or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, describe me now the characteristics of the outside aspect of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I don't know, separate from... What is that in its nature, the notion of outside?
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you even talk about it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... outside, it's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: The notion, any notion, what is it in its nature?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's... it's... it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically... What is it in its nature?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not what it's doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: A notion of this, a notion of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, any notion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any notion.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is a notion in its nature?
[SPEAKER_00]: A thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, within the... which is already thinking and pondering, possibility of speech is already a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have another thought within that thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: That says that I'm not a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am outside of these thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your notion of outside is an inside thought, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why there is an assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because of speech, not because of the principle of breaking into speech, turning away from... You can turn away from thoughts all you want, and speak all you want, and still not assume the thought to contradict itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, this is outside, and I can only think that on the inside.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can be free from assumptions and still speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Arhat wouldn't go mute.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not dwelling long enough on the characteristic of outside within your thoughts, you gratuitously maintain the notion of outside that's then carried and perpetuated with your speech that's affected by ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, this
[SPEAKER_01]: Speech... the possibility of speech is being the possibility of stepping outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's based upon this... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You should say like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Possibility of speech is possibility of turning away from thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not stepping outside.
[SPEAKER_00]: With ignorance, turning away from thoughts means being outside.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, as I said, outside of what?
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize, well, that's already a thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't be truly outside.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's what...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the only reason you're outside is because you don't fully understand you can't be outside.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I'm trying to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there can be speech without assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you now... you see...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you break out into speech, but that breaking out into speech cannot take you outside of the domain of thinking and pondering, because the whole domain of thinking and pondering is completely enclosed within... the whole domain of speech and the possibility of speech is enclosed within thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, all of your physical actions are enclosed within your mental intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: All your verbal actions are enclosed within mental intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, you want to take a thought of outside, allow it to endure, as that which says it's outside, and see the whole thing within the nature of being a thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you become incapable of assuming.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of maintaining upādāna, of perverting the order.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you realize that every single single example that could possibly arise of going outside, can't possibly be outside.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I said it many times, and I'll keep saying it.
[SPEAKER_00]: With Mahāmūgālāna, when the Buddha encouraged him to practice jhāna, which means he didn't have jhānas at the time, when the Buddha left, he sat under a tree and said, yeah, first jhāna, first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is first jhāna?
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't you get it by just staring at your nostrils?
[SPEAKER_00]: I think not.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think the Buddha would have said, instead of dwelling on these factors, characteristics of the first jhāna, why don't you just watch your nostrils, and it will happen to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: The overwhelming experience of joy you're going to have, then somebody will tell you, that was the jhāna, and then you will know it was the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you weren't conscious at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: You were kind of... You might have been slightly out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the point is, it needs to be understood, or at least recognized,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have a possibility to utter words with your mouth, and that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: However, if you're ignorant of the nature of that possibility, the nature of it being in us,
[SPEAKER_00]: The nature with being a saṅkhara, the necessary basis, the nature with being a container, that it cannot be stepped outside, then you committing to uttering words with your mouth, is then you assuming somehow pertaining to this external domain that is separate from
[SPEAKER_00]: The thinking and pondering of the possibility of the speech, that was there throughout, has to be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you suddenly stop thinking what you were about to say or what you were saying, you will stop speaking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so it's why samādhi, jhāna, is called unification of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's called imperturbable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not imperturbable in some majestic, mystical, transcendental sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's imperturbable because you have restored the right order that is now imperturbable.
[SPEAKER_00]: The definition of... like, turn something upside down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, now it's unturnable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind got established upon the right order and saw it as... And saw it as not optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: The wrong order was established.
[SPEAKER_00]: The perversions were there because you didn't realize they can't be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was the basis for them being there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you are responsible for their bhāva, for their being.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's fully assumed by you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But can you say as well, because it begins with thinking and pondering, this mental domain as being...
[SPEAKER_01]: That necessary base, that container, that nothing can step outside of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even any assumption of stepping outside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's enough for the complete liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: First jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Understanding the extent of that domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's unification of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more than enough for a full uprooting of all this, all the like, lust, aversion, delusion, all the suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't remember the sutra, but people can maybe mention in the comments, if they know the reference, where the Buddha says that... that... for the first...
[SPEAKER_00]: Which one?
[SPEAKER_00]: The first jhāna is... something like... Yeah, but he says that anāgāmī, being free from sensuality or final liberation, are dependent on the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they're undependent on the second jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or higher.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you can get the right view and everything else before that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But great, if you get it on the basis of first jhāna, there is very little work for you to do between being a sotāpanna and an arahant, if you already have developed mind to this imperturbable order of the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: What comes first is first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, isn't it marvelous?
[SPEAKER_00]: Putting second that which I was putting first, and putting first that which I was putting second.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fascinating.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't create anything, by the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even arahant can't create anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just undoes the mistake.
[SPEAKER_00]: The perversion of the order that was completely gratuitous.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't actually change the order.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't actually have the external domain of your speech independent of your thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, that's how you live.
[SPEAKER_00]: And for eons and eons and eons, because of your gratuitous assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you approve the assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing the maker of the raft and the rafters are destroyed and the maker of the house, as we were saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the maker.
[SPEAKER_00]: All these assumptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Gratuitous, little, assuming external in regard to this, giving it a separate identity, which in return defines you as an identity, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, once you stop,
[SPEAKER_01]: Assuming something external, then... How do you stop assuming something external?
[SPEAKER_01]: By including whatever it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: If any thought, any notion, any kind of something external, by recognizing that that has to be included within
[SPEAKER_01]: Really what?
[SPEAKER_01]: The necessary basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is what?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in this case, what you're talking about is thinking and pondering on the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within the...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't want to say within the mind, because everything is in my mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which kind of implies, oh, then there are other things that are outside of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the thought of outside of your mind, well, that's a thought which means it's within my mind, which means it's truly inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I think outside, or inside, or both, or neither, or in between, can all be done on the basis of the mind being there, the container of it, the container of the thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: The reason why I've just put mind up was because I was thinking Samādhi is the unification of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you see, I think the same principle can also be done, I think, like we're talking in the last talk, about the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can choose... That's why there are all those different
[SPEAKER_01]: The commentator is translating objects that you can use to develop first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Kammatthana.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're literally the same things that you can understand, the same principle, that you can establish the same right order.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where jhāna will be then.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can use the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Assuming outside of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you know that?
[SPEAKER_00]: As I asked you in the previous talk, when I recorded the kāramī yesterday before, well, when you're seeing things out there, like, distantly... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how could that... how could that thing...
[SPEAKER_01]: If the eye is not...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Necessary basis, that's right here.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, you're seeing the eye seeing things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the only relationship you can have with the world outside of your senses is the relationship that gets mirrored onto your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't see things that mirror things onto your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: You only see the mirror things on your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You only see the senses affected by these things, and then you assume those are the things outside of these senses, and that's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you conceive matter, or misconceive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any form of conceiving outside, as in conceiving the elements, conceiving the matter, as the Buddha said, it's misconceiving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so that's... that applies to any notion of something far away over there, outside of me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any notion of space or distance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or... or into... also in terms of time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Time, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: In terms of the future, which is... which I'm worried about, I'm thinking about that, because that's over there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's old, again.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's not here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does that... and that's what we're saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't... let's say... it doesn't matter if it's before, later, eh... old, new, big, small, up, down.
[SPEAKER_00]: matter, or feeling, or intention, or perception, matter is there, feeling is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, I have thoughts of past.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, stop thinking, stop thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's another thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you say, you think you stop thinking while you're thinking, and you're actually deluding yourself even further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you think about past, you plan about the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you do that in any other way, except thinking, right here, right now, presently, right here, right now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize, instead of you trying to interfere with it and prevent it, I must stop planning or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you must stop acting carelessly out of your plans, but that's a completely separate domain of you choosing to act.
[SPEAKER_00]: But thoughts of your plans, thoughts of your past, are thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all you're concerned about.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't care the content of your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: You care about... it's a thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the thought is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the thought is there, anything that
[SPEAKER_00]: Is in response to that thought, cannot be outside of the container of that thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence the intentionality behind your actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like one of the most fundamental and most practical things you can develop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you don't commit to full-on practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will result in, like, responsibility, transparency, confidence, strength and virtue, wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will result in wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you stop perverting the order.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the level of body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's unpervertable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not knowing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not knowing that?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your perversion, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you just keep acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, including the characteristic of outside, of this possible... of these thoughts of possibility of speaking while I'm not speaking, that's how you cease to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Including the characteristic of outside, characteristic that is sort of bundled with, that is sort of implied in possibility of breaking into speech, possibility to break into outside.
[SPEAKER_00]: That last bit of outside, you include as within the domain of thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Develop that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Develop clarity in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: At that time, that's the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: At that time, your sees... your speech has ceased.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when you go and break into... You're speechless in the sense that... Well, in the sense that... You're... you're... you now... any possibility to speak does not involve an assumption of going outside... Outside, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...of the thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then... then you might wonder, so, how can you speak ever again, afterwards, once you've undone the assumption?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can still speak without changing that assumption, without kind of... That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: You assuming outside is an extra step.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Assuming outside is an extension of the looking away from the thoughts towards the speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where it ends.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's hard to see.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you just naturally assume a better ending, which is outside world.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you're responsible for it, because it's not there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, turning away from thoughts in order to speak is a necessary basis for speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a necessary action behind the speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Turning away from thoughts with ignorance assumes the are.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm turning away from thoughts from here, I'm turning over there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you stop going that far, you will still be able to speak without assuming external world of speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are temporarily looking away from the thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the nature of speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: Breaking into speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: But...
[SPEAKER_01]: Same with body action, by the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that turning away doesn't involve a kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Assuming the separate domain where this turning away will occur, because that's contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all you need to do is approve the assumption from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why do... why is this assumption of outside so strong, so alluring, so... obviously because there's some...
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasure involved in the assumption of something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I can see now... Well, there's a pleasure in the nature of upādāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter necessarily the content.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, if it's a upādāna about the speech or upādāna about self-view.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's about the outsideness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I'm trying to get at.
[SPEAKER_00]: Outside-ness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's something about externality, which in itself is pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because
[SPEAKER_01]: It's beyond this pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's beyond this situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or at least, it allows possibility to be beyond this situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that is rooted... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that is rooted in you not wanting... Well, rooted in you feeling the pressure of the situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which you crave against.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why you're wanting this sex.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why you then engage with assumptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is beginningless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Gratuitous, but beginningless, as the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no discernible beginning before which avijjā wasn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: There was no ignorance, and suddenly it became ignorant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why it comes hand in hand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not expecting something outside or beyond, and...
[SPEAKER_00]: Resisting and accepting... No, you can expect.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can expect things outside, and then include your expectation within the domain of thought, fully contained within it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, literally, with this, I have these expectations.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: With manifestations of this necessary basis, these things are possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's Parthitsa Upadhyay's definition.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I was just trying to say that, like, that not...
[SPEAKER_01]: The extent to which you're expecting something external, outside, is to do with how your inability to withstand what's present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, that's more like now on the level of sensual assumptions, the extent of the desire and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, when you have obviously kind of withdrawn yourself from that, the expectation of how external speech is, it's not necessarily corresponding to how much you don't want your thoughts or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically just another principle that kind of fits into your already existing assumptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it gets taken by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why once you abandon the assumptions, these principles can still remain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thinking, speaking...
[SPEAKER_00]: But you won't be able to think, speak or act out of lust, out of aversion, out of those
[SPEAKER_00]: Perversions, they're direct result of ignorance, direct result of assumptions, of chasing the pleasure, chasing the external or getting rid of the... whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Assuming the external to basically overcome the unpleasantly enduring pressure of the feeling you're subjected to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Failing to see that the external is...
[SPEAKER_00]: Failing to see that all of it has to be rooted in the container of your craving against this feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now, when you're not speaking, when you go back to your kuti, you're not speaking, think about possibility to speak, because it has to be done presently.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't be careless.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't get distracted while you're thinking about a possibility of speaking, but not speaking.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's already a form of mindful thinking, or less unmindful thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's what we said at the beginning, that you cannot speak and still not be in the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not all you have to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why are you not in jhāna?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the domain of the... the extent of this domain of speech, which includes possibility of breaking into speech, hasn't been understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it hasn't been understood because you haven't been thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in order to think about it, one has to dwell on the present possibility to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: To speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then start discerning the kind of gratuitous implication of outside, which is a characteristic of that possibility at the moment, and then put that characteristic within the possibility, not maintain its notion that it's separate from it and outside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, put that which you're putting first, put it second.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the clearest description of how to enter jhāna I've ever heard.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You develop that, jhāna is the necessary result.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like, oh, we'll do this technique and that, and then, hopefully, it will happen to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you do all the meditation with that implicit hope.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's tied in with understanding, with clarity, with imperturbability.